Please welcome former director of AI
欢迎特斯拉人工智能公司前任总监
Tesla Andre Carpathy.
安德烈·卡帕西。
[Music]
[音乐]
Hello.
你好。
Wow, a lot of people here. Hello.
哇，这里人真多。 你好。
Um, okay. Yeah. So I'm excited to be
嗯，好的。 是的。 今天我很高兴能来到
here today to talk to you about software
这里，和大家谈谈
in the era of AI. And I'm told that many
人工智能时代的软件发展。 我听说
of you are students like bachelors,
你们当中有很多是学生，比如本科生、
masters, PhD and so on. And you're about
硕士生、博士生等等。 你即将
to enter the industry. And I think it's
进入这个行业。 我认为现在正是
very interesting time to enter the
进入这个行业的极其独特且非常有趣的时机
industry right now. And I think
。 我认为
fundamentally the reason for that is
根本原因在于
that um software is changing uh again.
软件又在发生变化。
And I say again because I actually gave
我再说一遍，因为我其实已经做过
this talk already. Um but the problem is
这个演讲了。 但问题是
that software keeps changing. So I
软件一直在变化。 所以，我
actually have a lot of material to
其实有很多素材可以用来
create new talks and I think it's
做新的演讲，而且我认为这种情况正在发生
changing quite fundamentally. I think
根本性的变化。 我认为，
roughly speaking software has not
粗略地说，软件
changed much on such a fundamental level
在如此根本的层面上，
for 70 years. And then it's changed I
70年来并没有发生太大的变化。 然后，我
think about twice quite rapidly in the
认为在过去的几年里，它发生了两次相当迅速的变化
last few years. And so there's just a
。 因此，需要
of software to write and rewrite. So
编写和重写大量的软件，工作量非常大。 那么，
let's take a look at maybe the realm of
让我们来看看
software. So if we kind of think of this
软件领域吧。 所以，如果我们把它想象成
as like the map of software this is a
软件的地图，那么这个
really cool tool called map of GitHub.
叫做 GitHub 地图的工具就非常酷。
Um this is kind of like all the software
嗯，这有点像所有已
that's written. Uh these are
编写的软件。 呃，这些是
instructions to the computer for
给计算机的指令，用于
carrying out tasks in the digital space.
在数字空间中执行任务。
So if you zoom in here, these are all
所以，如果你放大这里，你会发现这些都是
different kinds of repositories and this
不同类型的存储库，而这些
is all the code that has been written.
就是所有已编写的代码。
And a few years ago I kind of observed
几年前，我注意到
that um software was kind of changing
软件正在发生变化，出现了
and there was kind of like a new type of
一种新型
software around and I called this
软件，我
software 2.0 at the time and the idea
当时称之为软件 2.0，其理念
here was that software 1.0 is the code
是软件 1.0 是
you write for the computer. Software 2.0
你为计算机编写的代码。 软件 2.0
know are basically neural networks and
本质上就是神经网络，
in particular the weights of a neural
特别是神经网络的权重。
network and you're not writing this code
你不会直接编写这些代码，
directly you are most you are more kind
你更多的是在
of like tuning the data sets and then
调整数据集，然后
you're running an optimizer to create to
运行优化器来
create the parameters of this neural net
创建神经网络的参数。
and I think like at the time neural nets
我认为当时神经网络
were kind of seen as like just a
被视为一种
different kind of classifier like a
不同的分类器，比如
decision tree or something like that and
决策树之类的。
so I think it was kind of like um I
所以我觉得
think this framing was a lot more
这种说法更
appropriate and now actually what we
合适。而现在，我们拥有的，实际上就像是
GitHub in the realm of software 2.0 And
软件 2.0 领域的 GitHub。
I think the hugging face is basically
我认为这个拥抱脸基本上就是
equivalent of GitHub in software 2.0.
软件 2.0 领域的 GitHub。   此外，
And there's also model atlas and you can
还有模型图谱，您可以
visualize all the code written there. In
可视化其中编写的所有代码。 顺便一提，如果
case you're curious, by the way, the
你好奇的话，那个
giant circle, the point in the middle,
巨大的圆圈，中间的点，
uh these are the parameters of flux, the
呃，这些是
image generator. And so anytime someone
图像生成器 flux 的参数。 因此，每当有人在
tunes a on top of a flux model, you
Flux 模型之上进行调整时，你
basically create a git commit uh in this
基本上会在这个空间中创建一个 git 提交，
space and uh you create a different kind
然后创建一个不同类型的
of a image generator. So basically what
图像生成器。 所以基本上，
we have is software 1.0 is the computer
我们现在拥有的软件 1.0 就是对
code that programs a computer. Software
计算机进行编程的计算机代码。 软件
2.0 are the weights which program neural
2.0 是用于对神经网络进行编程的权重
networks. Uh and here's an example of
。 嗯，这里有一个
Alexet image recognizer neural network.
Alexet 图像识别神经网络的例子。
Now so far all of the neural networks
到目前为止，我们所熟悉的神经网络都
recently where kind of like fixed
像是固定
function computers image to categories
功能的计算机，比如将图像分类之类的
or something like that. And I think
。 我认为已经发生
what's changed and I think is a quite
改变的，而且我认为是一个相当
fundamental change is that neural
根本的改变，就是神经
networks became programmable with large
网络变得可以编程，并能构建大型
language models. And so I I see this as
语言模型。 所以我认为这
quite new, unique. It's a new kind of a
很新颖，很独特。 它是一种新型的
computer and uh so in my mind it's uh
计算机，所以在我看来，
worth giving it a new designation of
值得给它赋予一个新的名称——
software 3.0. And basically your prompts
软件 3.0。 基本上，你的提示
are now programs that program the LLM.
现在就是对LLM进行编程的程序。   令人惊讶的是，
And uh remarkably uh these uh prompts
这些提示都是
are written in English. So it's kind of
用英文写的。 所以它是一种
a very interesting programming language.
非常有趣的编程语言。
Um so maybe uh to summarize the
嗯，所以，总结一下
difference if you're doing sentiment
区别，例如，如果你要做情感
classification for example you can
分类，你可以想象
imagine writing some uh amount of Python
编写一些 Python 代码
to to basically do sentiment
来进行情感
classification or you can train a neural
分类，或者你可以训练一个神经
net or you can prompt a large language
网络，或者你可以训练一个大型语言
model. Uh so here this is a few short
模型。 嗯，这里有一些简短的
prompt and you can imagine changing it
提示，你可以想象一下，改变它
and programming the computer in a
并以
slightly different way. So basically we
略微不同的方式对计算机进行编程。 所以基本上我们
have software 1.0 software 2.0 and I
有了软件 1.0 和软件 2.0，而且我
think we're seeing maybe you've seen a
认为我们看到，也许你已经看到了
lot of GitHub code is not just like code
很多 GitHub 代码，它们不再仅仅是代码了
anymore. there's a bunch of like English
。
interspersed with code and so I think
代码中穿插着很多英文​​，所以我认为一种
new kind of code. So not only is it a
新型代码正在不断涌现。 所以，这不仅是一种
new programming paradigm, it's also
新的编程范式，而且令
remarkable to me that it's in our native
我感到惊讶的是，它竟然是用我们的母语
language of English. And so when this
英语编写的。 所以，几年前，当这件事让我大吃一惊时，
now I tweeted this and um I think it
我发了这条推文，嗯，我想它
captured the attention of a lot of
引起了很多人的关注，
people and this is my currently pinned
这条推文目前被我置顶了，内容是：
tweet uh is that remarkably we're now
我们现在竟然用
programming computers in English. Now,
英语编写计算机程序，这真是太不可思议了。
when I was at uh Tesla, um we were
我在特斯拉的时候，我们正在研发自动
working on the uh autopilot and uh we
驾驶系统，
were trying to get the car to drive and
努力让汽车能够自主行驶。当时
I sort of showed this slide at the time
我展示了一张幻灯片，
where you can imagine that the inputs to
你可以想象，
the car are on the bottom and they're
汽车的输入信号在底部，它们
going through a software stack to
通过一个软件栈来
produce the steering and acceleration
产生转向和加速。
and I made the observation at the time
我当时注意到，自动驾驶系统里
that there was a ton of C++ code around
有很多 C++ 代码，
in the autopilot which was the software
那是
1.0 code and then there was some neural
1.0 版本的软件代码，里面还有一些神经
nets in there doing image recognition
网络用于图像识别。
and uh I kind of observed that over time
我观察到，
as we made the autopilot better
随着我们不断改进自动驾驶系统，
basically the neural network grew in
神经网络的
capability and size and in addition to
功能和规模都在不断增长。除此之外，
that all the C++ code was being deleted
所有的 C++ 代码都被删除了，
and kind of like was um and a lot of the
很多
that was originally written in 1.0 was
最初在 1.0 版本中编写的功能都被
migrated to 2.0. So as an example, a lot
迁移到了 2.0 版本。 例如，
across images from the different cameras
来自不同摄像头
and across time was done by a neural
和不同时间点的图像信息拼接工作大多由神经
network and we were able to delete a lot
网络完成，我们得以删除大量
of code and so the software 2.0 stack
代码，因此 2.0 版软件栈
quite literally ate through the software
实际上完全取代了
stack of the autopilot. So I thought
自动驾驶仪的软件栈。 所以当时我觉得
this was really remarkable at the time
这非常了不起，
and I think we're seeing the same thing
而且我认为我们现在又看到了同样的事情，
again where uh basically we have a new
基本上我们有一种新型
kind of software and it's eating through
软件，它正在蚕食整个技术
the stack. We have three completely
栈。 我们有三种完全
different programming paradigms and I
不同的编程范式，我
think if you're entering the industry
认为如果你要进入这个行业，
it's a very good idea to be fluent in
最好精通所有这些范式，
all of them because they all have slight
因为它们各有
pros and cons and you may want to
优缺点，你可能需要用
program some functionality in 1.0 or 2.0
1.0、2.0 或 3.0 编写一些功能
or 3.0. Are you going to train
。 你打算训练
neurallet? Are you going to just prompt
神经网络吗？ 你打算直接申请
an LLM? Should this be a piece of code
法学硕士学位吗？ 这是否应该是一段
that's explicit etc. So we all have to
明确的代码等等。所以我们都必须
make these decisions and actually
做出这些决定，并且实际上
potentially uh fluidly trans transition
可能需要在
between these paradigms. So what I
这些范式之间流畅地过渡。 所以，我
wanted to get into now is first I want
现在想谈的是，首先我想
to in the first part talk about LLMs and
在第一部分谈谈法学硕士（LLM），以及
how to kind of like think of this new
如何看待这种新的
paradigm and the ecosystem and what that
范式和生态系统，以及它的样子
looks like. Uh like what are what is
。 呃，
this new computer? What does it look
这台新电脑是什么？ 它的外观如何？其
like and what does the ecosystem look
生态系统又是怎样的
like? Um I was struck by this quote from
？ 嗯，我被安杜林的这句话深深打动了，
Anduring actually uh many years ago now
其实那是很多年前的事了，
I think and I think Andrew is going to
我想安德鲁
be speaking right after me. Uh but he
接下来就要发言了。 呃，但他
said at the time AI is the new
当时说人工智能是新的
electricity and I do think that it um
电力，而且我认为这句话确实
kind of captures something very
抓住了一些非常
interesting in that LLMs certainly feel
有趣的东西，那就是LLM（生命周期管理）现在确实感觉
like they have properties of utilities
具有公用事业的特性
right now. So
。 所以
um LLM labs like OpenAI, Gemini,
像 OpenAI、Gemini、
Enthropic etc. They spend capex to train
Enthropic 等 LLM 实验室，他们会投入资本支出来训练
the LLMs and this is kind of equivalent
LLM，这有点像
to building out a grid and then there's
建设电网。然后，他们还需要投入运营支出，
opex to serve that intelligence over
通过
APIs to all of us and this is done
API 向我们所有人提供这些智能服务。这是
through metered access where we pay per
通过计量接入实现的，我们按每
million tokens or something like that
百万个代币或其他类似方式付费。
and we have a lot of demands that are
我们
very utility- like demands out of this
对这个 API 有很多类似公用事业的需求，比如
API we demand low latency high uptime
低延迟、高正常运行时间、
consistent quality etc. In electricity,
一致的质量等等。在电力行业，这就
you would have a transfer switch. So you
相当于一个转换开关。 所以你
can transfer your electricity source
可以将电力来源
from like grid and solar or battery or
从电网、太阳能、蓄电池或
generator. In LLM, we have maybe open
发电机等转移过来。 在 LLM 中，我们可能有一个开放式
router and easily switch between the
路由器，并且可以轻松地在
different types of LLMs that exist.
不同类型的 LLM 之间切换。
Because the LLM are software, they don't
因为LLM是软件，所以它们不
compete for physical space. So it's okay
争夺物理空间。 所以，
to have basically like six electricity
基本上可以有六家电力
providers and you can switch between
供应商，而且可以在它们之间切换
them, right? Because they don't compete
，对吧？ 因为它们之间并非
in such a direct way. And I think what's
直接竞争。 而且我觉得还有一点很
also a little fascinating and we saw
有意思，我们
this in the last few days actually a lot
最近几天也看到了这种情况，很多
of the LLMs went down and people were
LLM服务器都宕机了，人们被
kind of like stuck and unable to work.
困住了，无法工作。
And uh I think it's kind of fascinating
我觉得很有意思的是，
to me that when the state-of-the-art
当最先进的
LLMs go down, it's actually kind of like
LLM系统瘫痪时，实际上就像
an intelligence brownout in the world.
世界情报系统出现了一次中断。
It's kind of like when the voltage is
这就像
unreliable in the grid and uh the planet
电网电压不稳定一样，而且，
just gets dumber the more reliance we
我们越依赖
have on these models, which already is
这些模型，地球就越愚蠢，这种情况已经
like really dramatic and I think will
非常严重了，我认为还会
continue to grow. But LLM's don't only
继续恶化。 但LLM不仅
have properties of utilities. I think
具有效用函数的性质。 我认为
it's also fair to say that they have
也可以公平地说，它们具有
some properties of fabs. And the reason
一些晶圆厂的特性。 原因
for this is that the capex required for
在于，
building LLM is actually quite large. Uh
建造LLM所需的资本支出实际上相当大。 呃，
it's not just like building some uh
这可不是建个
power station or something like that,
发电站之类的东西，
right? You're investing a huge amount of
对吧？ 你投入了巨额
money and I think the tech tree and uh
资金，我认为科技树以及相关的
for the technology is growing quite
技术发展速度非常
rapidly. So we're in a world where we
快。 所以我们现在身处的世界里，
have sort of deep tech trees, research
存在着某种深厚的技术体系，
and development secrets that are
研发机密都
centralizing inside the LLM labs. Um and
集中在LLM实验室里。 嗯，
but I think the analogy muddies a little
不过我觉得这个类比有点模糊不清，
bit also because as I mentioned this is
因为正如我提到的，这是
software and software is a bit less
软件，而软件的
defensible because it is so malleable.
可塑性很强，所以辩护起来就没那么容易了。   所以，
And so um I think it's just an
嗯，我觉得这可能是一个值得
interesting kind of thing to think about
思考的有趣问题
potentially. There's many analogy
。
analogies you can make like a 4
你可以做很多类比，比如 4
nanometer process node maybe is
纳米工艺节点可能就像
something like a cluster with certain
一个具有特定
max flops. You can think about when
最大浮点运算次数的集群。 你可以想想当
you're use when you're using Nvidia GPUs
你使用 Nvidia GPU 时，
and you're only doing the software and
你只负责软件开发而不
you're not doing the hardware. That's
涉及硬件开发的情况。 这
kind of like the fabless model. But if
有点像无晶圆厂模式。 但如果
you're actually also building your own
你真的在构建自己的
hardware and you're training on TPUs if
硬件，并且像谷歌那样在 TPU 上进行训练
you're Google, that's kind of like the
，那有点像
Intel model where you own your fab. So I
英特尔的模式，你拥有自己的晶圆厂。 所以我
think there's some analogies here that
认为这里有一些
make sense. But actually I think the
合理的类比。 但实际上，我认为
analogy that makes the most sense
最合理的类比
perhaps is that in my mind LLM have very
或许是，在我看来，LLM
strong kind of analogies to operating
与操作系统有着非常强烈的相似之处
systems. Uh in that this is not just
。 嗯，因为这不仅仅是
electricity or water. It's not something
电力或水的问题。 它不是那种随处可得的
commodity. uh this is these are now
商品。 嗯，这些现在的
increasingly complex software ecosystems
软件生态系统越来越复杂，对吧？
right so uh they're not just like simple
所以它们不再像电力那样只是简单的
commodities like electricity and it's
商品。
kind of interesting to me that the
我觉得很有意思的是，这个
ecosystem is shaping in a very similar
生态系统的形成方式非常相似，
kind of way where you have a few closed
既有一些闭
source providers like Windows or Mac OS
源供应商，比如 Windows 或 Mac OS，
and then you have an open source
也有像
alternative like Linux and I think for u
Linux 这样的开源替代方案。我认为对于
neural for LLMs as well we have a kind
Linux 来说，也存在着
of a few competing closed source
一些相互竞争的闭源
providers and then maybe the llama
供应商，而 Linux 生态
ecosystem is currently like maybe a
系统目前可能与未来
may grow into something like Linux.
发展成类似 Linux 的生态系统非常接近。
Again, I think it's still very early
再次强调，我认为现在还为时尚早，
because these are just simple LLMs, but
因为这些只是简单的LLM，但
we're starting to see that these are
我们开始看到它们将会
going to get a lot more complicated.
变得更加复杂。
It's not just about the LLM itself. It's
这不仅仅关乎法学硕士学位本身。 它
about all the tool use and the
涉及到所有工具的使用、
multiodalities and how all of that
多种功能以及所有这些是如何
works. And so when I sort of had this
运作的。 所以，前段时间我
realization a while back, I tried to
意识到这一点后，就试着把它
sketch it out and it kind of seemed to
画出来，我觉得
me like LLMs are kind of like a new
LLM就像一个新的
operating system, right? So the LLM is a
操作系统，对吧？ 所以LLM是一种
new kind of a computer. It's sitting
新型计算机。 它就像
it's kind of like the CPU equivalent. uh
CPU的替代品一样，静静地待在那里。
the context windows are kind of like the
上下文窗口有点像
memory and then the LLM is orchestrating
内存，而 LLM 则协调
memory and compute uh for problem
内存和计算，
solving um using all of these uh
利用所有这些功能来解决问题，所以
operating system from that perspective.
从这个角度来看，它确实很像操作系统。
Um, a few more analogies. For example,
嗯，再举几个例子。 例如，
if you want to download an app, say I go
如果你想下载一个应用程序，假设我
to VS Code and I go to download, you can
打开 VS Code 并点击下载，你就可以
download VS Code and you can run it on
下载 VS Code，然后你可以在
Windows, Linux or or Mac in the same way
Windows、Linux 或 Mac 上运行它，就像
as you can take an LLM app like cursor
你可以下载一个 LLM 应用程序（例如 Cursor）
and you can run it on GPT or cloud or
并在 GPT、云端或 Gemini 系列上运行它一样
Gemini series, right? It's just a drop
，对吧？ 就是一个下拉菜单
down. So, it's kind of like similar in
。 所以，从这个意义上来说，它们也有些相似
that way as well.
。
uh more analogies that I think strike me
嗯，我觉得更贴切的类比
is that we're kind of like in this
是，我们现在有点像回到了
1960sish
20 世纪 60
era where LLM compute is still very
年代，LLM 计算
expensive for this new kind of a
对于这种新型
computer and that forces the LLMs to be
计算机来说仍然非常昂贵，这迫使 LLM
centralized in the cloud and we're all
集中在云端，而我们都
just uh sort of thing clients that
只是通过
interact with it over the network and
网络与之交互的客户端，
none of us have full utilization of
我们谁都无法充分利用
these computers and therefore it makes
这些计算机，因此
sense to use time sharing where we're
使用分时技术就很有意义，我们每个人都
all just you know a dimension of the
只是云端计算机运行期间批处理任务的一个维度
in the cloud. And this is very much what
。 这就是
computers used to look like at during
当时电脑的大致样子
this time. The operating systems were in
。 操作系统位于
the cloud. Everything was streamed
云端。 所有内容都通过流媒体传输，
around and there was batching. And so
并且采用批量处理的方式。 因此，
the p the personal computing revolution
个人计算革命
hasn't happened yet because it's just
尚未发生，因为它在
not economical. It doesn't make sense.
经济上是不可行的。 这说不通。
But I think some people are trying. And
但我认为有些人正在尝试。 事实
it turns out that Mac minis, for
证明，例如 Mac mini
example, are a very good fit for some of
非常适合某些
the LLMs because it's all if you're
LLM，因为如果你
doing batch one inference, this is all
进行的是批量推理，那么所有推理都受到
super memory bound. So this actually
内存的极大限制。 所以这方法确实
works.
有效。   嗯，
And uh I think these are some early
我认为这些
indications maybe of personal computing.
可能是个人计算的早期迹象。
Uh but this hasn't really happened yet.
呃，但这事还没真正发生呢。   目前还
It's not clear what this looks like.
不清楚这看起来是什么样子。
Maybe some of you get to invent what
也许你们中的一些人可以发明
what this is or how it works or uh what
这是什么，或者它是如何运作的，或者它
this should what this should be. Maybe
应该是什么样子。
one more analogy that I'll mention is
我再举一个例子：
whenever I talk to Chach or some LLM
每当我直接用文字与 Chach 或某些 LLM 交谈时
directly in text, I feel like I'm
，我都感觉自己像是在
talking to an operating system through
通过终端与操作系统对话
the terminal. Like it's just it's it's
。 就像它只是一段
text. It's direct access to the
文字。 这是对操作系统的直接访问
operating system. And I think a guey
。 而且我认为，像科技泡沫之外的那种普遍意义上的泡沫，还
hasn't yet really been invented in like
没有真正被发明出来
bubbles. Uh certainly some of the apps
。 嗯，当然，我们稍后要介绍的一些应用程序
have guey but there's no like guey
有 guey，但并非
across all the tasks if that makes
所有任务都有 guey，如果我这么说你能
sense. Um there are some ways in which
理解的话。 嗯，LLM 在某些方面与
operating systems in some fairly unique
操作系统
way and from early computing. And I
和早期计算机有所不同，而且在某些方面相当独特。 我
wrote about uh this one particular
写到了一处与
different uh this time around. It's that
以往截然不同的房产。 就像
LLMs like flip they flip the direction
LLM一样，它们会改变
of technology diffusion uh that is
技术扩散的方向，而技术扩散
usually uh present in technology. So for
通常存在于技术领域。
example with electricity, cryptography,
例如电力、密码学、
computing, flight, internet, GPS, lots
计算机、航空、互联网、GPS 等许多以前从未出现过的
of new transformative technologies that
变革性新技术
have not been around. Typically it is
。 通常情况下，
the government and corporations that are
政府和企业是
the first users because it's new and
第一批用户，因为这项技术是新技术，价格
expensive etc. and it only later
昂贵等等，之后才会
diffuses to consumer. Uh, but I feel
普及到消费者群体。 呃，但我感觉
like LLMs are kind of like flipped
法学硕士（LLM）有点像是颠倒
around. So maybe with early computers,
过来的。 所以，早期的计算机可能都与
it was all about ballistics and military
弹道学和军事
use, but with LLMs, it's all about how
用途有关，但对于LLM来说，它却可以用来解决如何
do you boil an egg or something like
煮鸡蛋之类的问题
that. This is certainly like a lot of my
。 这确实很像我的很多
use. And so it's really fascinating to
使用习惯。 所以，让我感到非常神奇的是，
me that we have a new magical computer
我们拥有了一台神奇的新电脑，
and it's like helping me boil an egg.
它就像帮我煮鸡蛋一样简单。   它对
It's not helping the government do
政府开展一些
something really crazy like some
真正疯狂的项目，比如
military ballistics or some special
军事弹道学或特殊
technology. Indeed, corporations are
技术，并没有帮助。 事实上，企业和
governments are lagging behind the
政府在
adoption of all of us, of all of these
采用所有这些技术方面都落后于我们所有人
technologies. So, it's just backwards
。 所以，这完全是本末倒置，
and I think it informs maybe some of the
我认为这或许能启发
uses of how we want to use this
我们思考如何使用这项
technology or like where are some of the
技术，或者
first apps and so on.
最早的一些应用程序在哪里等等。
So, in summary so far, LLM labs LLMs. I
综上所述，到目前为止，LLM 实验室 LLM。 我
think it's accurate language to use, but
认为这种说法很准确，但
LLMs are complicated operating systems.
LLM是复杂的操作系统。
They're circa 1960s in computing and
他们的计算机技术还停留在上世纪60年代的水平，而
we're redoing computing all over again.
我们正在重新开始计算机技术的发展。
and they're currently available via time
目前，它们通过分时
sharing and distributed like a utility.
共享的方式提供，并像公用事业一样进行分配。
What is new and unprecedented is that
前所未有的是，
they're not in the hands of a few
它们不再掌握在少数
governments and corporations. They're in
政府和企业手中。 它们掌握在
the hands of all of us because we all
我们所有人手中，因为我们
have a computer and it's all just
都有一台电脑，而这一切都只是
software and Chaship was beamed down to
软件，Chaship 就像一夜之间瞬间被传送到
our computers like billions of people
数十亿人的电脑上一样，
like instantly and overnight and this is
这太
insane. Uh and it's kind of insane to me
疯狂了。 呃，我觉得
that this is the case and now it is our
这有点不可思议，现在竟然是我们
time to enter the industry and program
进入这个行业，为这些计算机编写程序的时候了
these computers. This is crazy. So I
。 这太疯狂了。 所以我
think this is quite remarkable. Before
认为这非常了不起。 在
we program LLMs, we have to kind of like
编写 LLM 程序之前，我们需要
spend some time to think about what
花些时间思考一下
these things are. And I especially like
这些东西是什么。 我尤其喜欢探讨
to kind of talk about their psychology.
他们的心理。
So the way I like to think about LLMs is
所以我喜欢把法学硕士看作是
that they're kind of like people
人的
spirits. Um they are stoastic
灵魂。 嗯，它们是
simulations of people. Um and the
对人的冷静模拟。 嗯，而
simulator in this case happens to be an
本例中的模拟器恰好是一个
auto reggressive transformer. So
自递增变压器。 所以
transformer is a neural net. Uh it's and
Transformer是一种神经网络。 嗯，
it just kind of like is goes on the
它就像是代
level of tokens. It goes chunk chunk
币级别的。 它断断续续地进行着
chunk chunk chunk. And there's an almost
。 而且
equal amount of compute for every single
每个数据块的计算量几乎相等
chunk. Um and um this simulator of
。 嗯，这个模拟器
course is is just is basically there's
当然只是基本上
some weights involved and we fit it to
涉及到一些权重，我们把它拟合到
all of text that we have on the internet
我们在互联网上拥有的所有文本
and so on. And you end up with this kind
等等。 最终你会得到这样一种
of a simulator and because it is trained
模拟器，因为它是
on humans, it's got this emergent
在人类身上训练的，所以它具有类似
psychology that is humanlike. So the
人类的涌现心理。 所以
first thing you'll notice is of course
你首先会注意到的是，法学
uh LLM have encyclopedic knowledge and
硕士当然拥有百科全书般的知识和
memory. uh and they can remember lots of
记忆力。 嗯，而且他们能记住很多
things, a lot more than any single
东西，比任何一个
individual human can because they read
普通人都能记住得多，因为他们读过
so many things. It's it actually kind of
很多书。 这让
reminds me of this movie Rainman, which
我想起了电影《雨人》，
I actually really recommend people
我真心推荐大家
watch. It's an amazing movie. I love
去看这部电影。 这是一部很棒的电影。 我喜欢
this movie. Um and Dustin Hoffman here
这部电影。 嗯，达斯汀·霍夫曼
is an autistic savant who has almost
是一位自闭症天才，他的
perfect memory. So, he can read a he can
记忆力几乎完美。 所以，他能像读
read like a phone book and remember all
电话簿一样阅读，记住所有的
of the names and phone numbers. And I
名字和电话号码。 我
kind of feel like LM are kind of like
感觉LM和它们之间有点
very similar. They can remember Shaw
非常相似。 他们能非常轻松地记住肖氏
hashes and lots of different kinds of
哈希值以及各种各样的
things very very easily. So they
东西。 所以，
certainly have superpowers in some set
在某些方面，他们确实拥有超能力
in some respects. But they also have a
。 但他们也存在
bunch of I would say cognitive deficits.
一系列我认为是认知方面的缺陷。
So they hallucinate quite a bit. Um and
所以他们经常出现幻觉。 嗯，
they kind of make up stuff and don't
他们有点儿胡编乱造，而且没有
have a very good uh sort of internal
很好的、或者说足够完善的
model of self-nowledge, not sufficient
自我认知内部模型
at least. And this has gotten better but
。 情况有所改善，但
not perfect. They display jagged
还不完美。 他们展现出复杂而敏锐的
intelligence. So they're going to be
智慧。 所以他们
superhuman in some problems solving
在某些问题解决
domains. And then they're going to make
领域将会拥有超人的能力。 然后他们会犯一些
mistakes that basically no human will
基本上人类不会
make. like you know they will insist
犯的错误。 就像你知道的，他们会坚持
that 9.11 is greater than 9.9 or that
认为 9.11 大于 9.9，或者
there are two Rs in strawberry these are
草莓（strawberry）里有两个 R，这些都是
some famous examples but basically there
一些著名的例子，但基本上，他们的思维方式
are rough edges that you can trip on so
存在一些缺陷，你可能会因此而犯错，所以我
that's kind of I think also kind of
认为这也有点
unique um they also kind of suffer from
独特。嗯，他们似乎也患有顺
entrograde amnesia um so uh and I think
行性遗忘症。嗯，我想
I'm alluding to the fact that if you
暗示的是，如果
have a co-orker who joins your
你的组织里来了一位同事，
organization this co-orker will over
随着时间的推移，这位同事会
time learn your organization and uh they
了解你的组织，并逐渐
will understand and gain like a huge
掌握大量的
amount of context on the organization
组织背景信息。他们
and they go home and they sleep and they
回家睡觉后，会
consolidate knowledge and they develop
巩固知识，并随着
expertise over time. LLMs don't natively
时间的推移发展出专业技能。  LLM 本身并不
do this and this is not something that
具备这种功能，而且这也不是 LLM
has really been solved in the R&amp;D of
研发中真正解决的问题
LLM. I think um and so context windows
。 我认为上下文窗口
are really kind of like working memory
实际上有点像工作记忆，
and you have to sort of program the
你必须
working memory quite directly because
直接对工作记忆进行编程，因为
they don't just kind of like get smarter
它们不会默认变得更智能，
by uh by default and I think a lot of
我认为很多
people get tripped up by the analogies
人会被这种类比绊倒
uh in this way. Uh in popular culture I
。 在流行文化方面，我
recommend people watch these two movies
推荐大家观看这两部电影：《记忆
uh Momento and 51st dates. In both of
碎片》和《第51次约会》。 在
these movies, the protagonists, their
这两部电影中，主角们的
weights are fixed and their context
体重是固定的，他们的情境
windows gets wiped every single morning
窗口每天早上都会被清除，
work or have relationships when this
这种情况发生时，上班或建立人际关系都会非常麻烦，
happens and this happens to all the
而且这种情况还会持续发生
time. I guess one more thing I would
。 我想指出的另一点
point to is security kind of related
是
limitations of the use of LLM. So for
LLM使用中与安全相关的局限性。
example, LLMs are quite gullible. Uh
例如，法学硕士很容易上当受骗。 呃，
they are susceptible to prompt injection
他们容易受到快速注射
risks. They might leak your data etc.
风险的影响。 他们可能会泄露你的数据等等。
And so um and there's many other
所以，还有许多其他
considerations uh security related. So,
与安全相关的考虑因素。 所以，
so basically long story short, you have
简而言之，你
to load your you have to load your you
必须
have to simultaneously think through
同时思考
this superhuman thing that has a bunch
这个拥有大量
of cognitive deficits and issues. How do
认知缺陷和问题的超人般的存在。
we and yet they are extremely like
我们如何才能既利用它们又利用它们的巨大潜力，
useful and so how do we program them and
那么我们该如何对它们进行编程，
how do we work around their deficits and
如何克服它们的缺陷，并
enjoy their superhuman powers.
享受它们超人的力量呢？
So what I want to switch to now is talk
所以我现在想转而谈谈
about the opportunities of how do we use
我们如何利用
these models and what are some of the
这些模型，以及其中
biggest opportunities. This is not a
最大的机遇有哪些。 这并非一份
comprehensive list just some of the
完整的清单，只是
things that I thought were interesting
我认为与
for this talk. The first thing I'm kind
本次演讲相关的一些有趣内容。 我首先感到
of excited about is what I would call
兴奋的是我所谓的“
partial autonomy apps. So for example,
部分自主应用程序”。 例如，
let's work with the example of coding.
我们以编程为例。
You can certainly go to chacht directly
你当然可以直接去 chacht，然后
and you can start copy pasting code
开始到处复制粘贴代码
around and copyping bug reports and
、复制错误报告
stuff around and getting code and copy
等等，获取代码并复制
pasting everything around. Why would you
粘贴所有内容。 你为什么要
why would you do that? Why would you go
这么做？ 为什么要
directly to the operating system? It
直接进入操作系统？ 开发
makes a lot more sense to have an app
一个专门用于此的应用程序显然更有意义
dedicated for this. And so I think many
。 所以我觉得
of you uh use uh cursor. I do as well.
你们很多人都会使用光标。 我也是。
And uh cursor is kind of like the thing
而光标才是
you want instead. You don't want to just
你想要的那种东西。 你不想
directly go to the chash apt. And I
直接去现金公寓。 我
think cursor is a very good example of
认为 Cursor 是一个很好的
an early LLM app that has a bunch of
早期 LLM 应用程序示例，它有很多
properties that I think are um useful
属性，我认为这些属性
across all the LLM apps. So in
在所有 LLM 应用程序中都很有用。 因此
particular, you will notice that we have
，您会特别注意到，我们保留了
a traditional interface that allows a
传统的界面，允许
human to go in and do all the work
用户像以前一样手动完成所有工作
manually just as before. But in addition
。 但
to that, we now have this LLM
除此之外，我们现在还有 LLM
integration that allows us to go in
集成，这使我们能够进行
bigger chunks. And so some of the
更大幅度的操作。 因此，
properties of LLM apps that I think are
我认为LLM应用程序的一些
shared and useful to point out. Number
共同特性值得指出。
one, the LLMs basically do a ton of the
第一，LLM 基本上承担了大量的
context management. Um, number two, they
上下文管理工作。 嗯，第二点，他们会
orchestrate multiple calls to LLMs,
策划多次致电LLM，
right? So in the case of cursor, there's
对吧？ 所以，对于 cursor 来说，其
under the hood embedding models for all
底层包含了所有文件的嵌入模型
your files, the actual chat models,
、实际的聊天模型、将
models that apply diffs to the code, and
差异应用于代码的模型，
this is all orchestrated for you. A
所有这些都由它自动完成。 一个
really big one that uh I think also
非常重要但
maybe not fully appreciated always is
可能没有得到充分重视的方面是
application specific uh GUI and the
应用程序特定的图形用户界面及其
importance of it. Um because you don't
重要性。 嗯，因为你不想
system directly in text. Text is very
直接用文本与操作系统对话。 文本
hard to read, interpret, understand and
很难阅读、解读和理解，
also like you don't want to take some of
而且你也不想
these actions natively in text. So it's
直接在文本中执行某些操作。 所以
much better to just see a diff as like
最好直接看到差异，比如
red and green change and you can see
红色和绿色的变化，这样你就可以看到
what's being added is subtracted. It's
增加了什么，减少了什么。 最
much easier to just do command Y to
简单的办法就是直接输入命令 Y
accept or command N to reject. I
接受，或者输入命令 N 拒绝。 我
shouldn't have to type it in text,
应该不用打字吧
right? So, a guey allows a human to
？ 因此，guey 可以让人类
audit the work of these fallible systems
审核这些易出错的系统的工作，
and to go faster. I'm going to come back
从而加快速度。 我
to this point a little bit uh later as
稍后还会再谈到这一点
well. And the last kind of feature I
。 最后我
want to point out is that there's what I
想指出的功能是，我
call the autonomy slider. So, for
称之为自主性滑块。 例如
example, in cursor, you can just do tap
，在光标模式下，你可以直接进行点击
completion. You're mostly in charge. You
补全。 你基本上负责。 您
can select a chunk of code and command K
可以选择一段代码，然后按 K 键
to change just that chunk of code. You
来更改该段代码。 你
can do command L to change the entire
可以使用命令 L 来修改整个
file. Or you can do command I which just
文件。 或者你可以执行命令 I，也就是
you know let it rip do whatever you want
让它在整个仓库中执行任何你想做的事情，
in the entire repo and that's the sort
这是一种
of full autonomy agent agentic version
完全自主的代理版本，
and so you are in charge of the autonomy
因此你可以控制自主度
slider and depending on the complexity
滑块，并根据
of the task at hand you can uh tune the
手头任务的复杂性来调整
amount of autonomy that you're willing
你愿意
to give up uh for that task maybe to
为该任务放弃的自主度。也许再举一个
show one more example of a fairly
相当
successful LLM app uh perplexity um it
成功的 LLM 应用程序的例子，Perplexity，它
also has very similar features to what
也具有与
I've just pointed out to in cursor uh it
我刚才在 Cursor 中指出的非常相似的功能，它将
packages up a lot of the information. It
大量信息打包在一起。 它
orchestrates multiple LLMs. It's got a
协调多个LLM。 它有一个
GUI that allows you to audit some of its
图形用户界面，可以让你审核它的一些
work. So, for example, it will site
工作。 例如，它会显示网站
sources and you can imagine inspecting
资源，你可以想象一下如何检查
them. And it's got an autonomy slider.
它们。 它还配备了自主运行时间调节滑块。
You can either just do a quick search or
你可以快速搜索一下，也
you can do research or you can do deep
可以做一些研究，或者进行深入
research and come back 10 minutes later.
研究，10分钟后再回来。
So, this is all just varying levels of
所以，这一切都只是
autonomy that you give up to the tool.
你向工具放弃的不同程度的自主权而已。
So, I guess my question is I feel like a
所以，我想问的是，我觉得
lot of software will become partially
很多软件将会变得部分
autonomous. I'm trying to think through
自动化。 我正在努力思考，
like what does that look like? And for
那会是什么样子？ 对于
many of you who maintain products and
你们这些维护产品和
services, how are you going to make your
服务的人来说，你们将如何使你们的
products and services partially
产品和服务实现部分
autonomous? Can an LLM see everything
自主化？ 法学硕士能看到
that a human can see? Can an LLM act in
人类所能看到的一切吗？ 法学硕士能否像
all the ways that a human could act? And
人类一样行事？
can humans supervise and stay in the
人类能否监督并了解
loop of this activity? Because again,
这项活动的全部情况？ 因为
these are fallible systems that aren't
这些都是有缺陷的系统，它们还不
yet perfect. And what does a diff look
完美。
like in Photoshop or something like
在 Photoshop 之类的软件中，差异对比图是什么样的
that? You know, and also a lot of the
？ 你知道，
traditional software right now, it has
现在很多传统软件都有各种各样的
all these switches and all this kind of
开关和
stuff that's all designed for human. All
功能，这些都是为人类设计的。 所有
of this has to change and become
这些都必须改变，并向
accessible to LLMs.
法学硕士（LLM）学生开放。
So, one thing I want to stress with a
所以，我想强调一点，
lot of these LLM apps that I'm not sure
很多LLM应用程序并没有
gets as much attention as it should is
得到应有的关注，那就是
um we we're now kind of like cooperating
我们现在有点像是在
with AIS and usually they are doing the
与AIS合作，通常情况下，他们负责
generation and we as humans are doing
生成数据，而我们人类负责
the verification. It is in our interest
验证。
to make this loop go as fast as
让这个循环尽可能快地进行符合我们的利益
possible. So, we're getting a lot of
。 所以，我们完成了很多
work done. There are two major ways that
工作。 我认为有两种主要方法
I think uh this can be done. Number one,
可以实现这一点。 第一，
you can speed up verification a lot. Um,
您可以大大加快验证速度。 嗯，
and I think guies, for example, are
我认为例如 guey 就
extremely important to this because a
非常重要，因为
guey utilizes your computer vision GPU
guey 会利用我们大脑中的计算机视觉 GPU
in all of our head. Reading text is
。 阅读文字很
effortful and it's not fun, but looking
费力，也不好玩，但看
at stuff is fun and it's it's just a
东西很有趣，就像是通往
kind of like a highway to your brain.
大脑的一条高速公路。
So, I think guies are very useful for
所以，我认为 GUI 对于
auditing systems and visual
审计系统和
representations in general. And number
一般的视觉表示都非常有用。
two, I would say is we have to keep the
第二点，我认为我们必须控制
AI on the leash. We I think a lot of
人工智能。 我认为很多
people are getting way over excited with
人对
AI agents and uh it's not useful to me
人工智能代理过于兴奋了，而且对我来说，将
to get a diff of 10,000 lines of code to
10,000 行代码的差异添加到
my repo. Like I have to I'm still the
我的代码库中并没有用处。 我必须这么做，因为我仍然是
bottleneck, right? Even though that
瓶颈，对吧？ 即使这
10,00 lines come out instantly, I have
10,000 行代码瞬间就能输出，我也
to make sure that this thing is not
必须确保它不会
introducing bugs. It's just like and
引入错误。 就好像
that it's doing the correct thing,
它在做正确的事情一样，
right? And that there's no security
对吧？ 而且不存在安全
issues and so on. So um I think that um
问题等等。 所以，嗯，我认为，嗯，
yeah basically you we have to sort of
基本上，我们必须让
the flow of these two go very very fast
这两个过程进展得非常非常快，这符合我们的利益，
and we have to somehow keep the AI on
而且我们必须以某种方式控制人工智能，
the leash because it gets way too
因为它反应
overreactive. It's uh it's kind of like
过度了。 嗯，大概是这样的
this. This is how I feel when I do AI
。 这就是我进行人工智能
assisted coding. If I'm just bite coding
辅助编程时的感受。 如果我只是随便写写代码，那
everything is nice and great but if I'm
一切都很好，但如果我
actually trying to get work done it's
真的想完成工作，
not so great to have an overreactive uh
有个反应过度的
agent doing all this kind of stuff. So
代理做所有这些事情就不太好。 所以
this slide is not very good. I'm sorry,
这张幻灯片不太好。 很抱歉，
but I guess I'm trying to develop like
但我想我和你们中的许多人一样，正在尝试开发
many of you some ways of utilizing these
一些方法，
agents in my coding workflow and to do
在我的编码工作流程中利用这些代理，并进行
AI assisted coding. And in my own work,
人工智能辅助编码。 而我自己在工作中，
I'm always scared to get way too big
总是害怕出现太大的
diffs. I always go in small incremental
差异。 我总是
chunks. I want to make sure that
分小步进行。 我想确认
everything is good. I want to spin this
一切是否妥当。 我想让这个
loop very very fast and um I sort of
循环快速旋转，然后我慢慢地
work on small chunks of single concrete
处理一些小块的、具体的
thing. Uh and so I think many of you
东西。 所以我觉得你们中的很多人
probably are developing similar ways of
可能都在探索与法学硕士（
working with the with LLMs.
LLM）合作的类似方法。
Um, I also saw a number of blog posts
嗯，我还看到一些博客文章
that try to develop these best practices
试图总结与
for working with LLMs. And here's one
法学硕士合作的最佳实践。 这是
that I read recently and I thought was
我最近读过的一篇，我觉得
quite good. And it kind of discussed
很不错。 它讨论了
some techniques and some of them have to
一些技术，其中一些技术与
do with how you keep the AI on the
如何控制人工智能有关
leash. And so, as an example, if you are
。 举例来说，如果你发出
prompting, if your prompt is vague, then
提示，但提示很模糊，那么
uh the AI might not do exactly what you
人工智能可能不会完全按照你
wanted and in that case, verification
想要的方式操作，在这种情况下，验证
will fail. You're going to ask for
就会失败。 你还会提出
something else. If a verification fails,
其他要求。 如果验证失败，就会
then you're going to start spinning. So
开始空转。 因此，
it makes a lot more sense to spend a bit
花更多
more time to be more concrete in your
时间让你的
prompts which increases the probability
提示更具体一些更有意义，这样可以提高
of successful verification and you can
验证成功的概率，让你能够
move forward. And so I think a lot of us
继续前进。 所以我觉得我们很多人
are going to end up finding um kind of
最终都会找到类似这样的
techniques like this. I think in my own
技巧。 我认为在我自己的
work as well I'm currently interested in
工作中，我目前也对教育的未来发展方向很感兴趣，比如
together with kind of like now that we
现在我们
have AI uh and LLMs what does education
有了人工智能和法学硕士，教育的未来发展方向是什么
look like? And I think a a large amount
？ 我认为，我们应该认真
of thought for me goes into how we keep
思考如何控制
AI on the leash. I don't think it just
人工智能。 我觉得直接
works to go to chat and be like, "Hey,
去聊天室说“嘿，
teach me physics." I don't think this
教我物理吧”是行不通的。 我觉得这
works because the AI is like gets lost
行不通，因为人工智能就像
in the woods. And so for me, this is
在森林里迷路了一样。 所以对我来说，这
actually two separate apps. For example,
实际上是两个独立的应用程序。 例如，
there's an app for a teacher that
有一款教师应用程序，可以
creates courses and then there's an app
创建课程；还有一款应用程序，可以
that takes courses and serves them to
接收课程并将其提供给
students. And in both cases, we now have
学生。 在这两种情况下，我们现在都有了
this intermediate artifact of a course
这个可审核的课程中间成果，
that is auditable and we can make sure
我们可以确保
it's good. We can make sure it's
它是合格的。 我们可以确保其
consistent. and the AI is kept on the
一致性。 人工智能
leash with respect to a certain
在一定的
syllabus, a certain like um progression
教学大纲、一定的
of projects and so on. And so this is
项目进度等方面都受到限制。 所以这是
one way of keeping the AI on leash and I
控制人工智能的一种方法，我
think has a much higher likelihood of
认为这种方法成功的可能性要高得多，
working and the AI is not getting lost
人工智能也不会迷失方向
in the woods.
。
One more kind of analogy I wanted to
我想再提一个类比：
sort of allude to is I'm not I'm no
我
stranger to partial autonomy and I kind
对部分自动驾驶并不陌生，我在特斯拉
of worked on this I think for five years
工作了五年左右，这方面我也有所涉猎。
at Tesla and this is also a partial
这款产品也属于部分
autonomy product and shares a lot of the
自动驾驶产品，并有很多相似之处，
features like for example right there in
例如
the instrument panel is the GUI of the
仪表盘上的
autopilot so it's showing me what the
自动驾驶图形用户界面，它会显示
what the neural network sees and so on
神经网络看到的内容等等。
and we have the autonomy slider where
我们还有一个自动驾驶滑块，在
over the course of my tenure there we
我任职期间，我们
did more and more autonomous tasks for
为用户实现了越来越多的自动驾驶功能。
the user and maybe the story that I
我
wanted to tell very briefly is uh
想简单分享一下我的经历：
actually the first time I drove a
我第一次驾驶
self-driving vehicle was in 2013 and I
自动驾驶汽车是在2013年，当时我的
had a friend who worked at Whimo and uh
一个朋友在Whimo工作，
he offered to give me a drive around
他主动提出带我在
Palo Alto. I took this picture using
帕洛阿尔托附近兜风。 这张照片是我
Google Glass at the time and many of you
当时用谷歌眼镜拍摄的，你们当中很多人
are so young that you might not even
可能还很年轻，甚至不
know what that is. Uh but uh yeah, this
知道那是什么。 嗯，没错，这
was like all the rage at the time. And
在当时可是风靡一时。 然后
we got into this car and we went for
我们上了车，在
about a 30-minute drive around Palo Alto
帕洛阿尔托的
highways uh streets and so on. And this
公路、街道等等地方开了大约 30 分钟。 这次
drive was perfect. There was zero
自驾游非常完美。 当时没有任何
interventions and this was 2013 which is
干预措施，而这发生在 2013 年，距今已有
now 12 years ago. And it kind of struck
12 年了。 这让
me because at the time when I had this
我印象深刻，因为当时我进行了一次
perfect drive, this perfect demo, I felt
完美的驾驶，一次完美的演示，我
like, wow, self-driving is imminent
觉得，哇，自动驾驶指日可待，
because this just worked. This is
因为它真的成功了。 这太
incredible. Um, but here we are 12 years
不可思议了。 嗯，但是12年
later and we are still working on
过去了，我们仍在致力于实现
autonomy. Um, we are still working on
自主化。 嗯，我们仍在研究
driving agents and even now we haven't
驾驶代理，即使现在我们还没有
actually like really solved the problem.
真正解决这个问题。
like you may see Whimos going around and
就像你可能看到Whimos在路上行驶，
they look driverless but you know
它们看起来像是无人驾驶的，但你知道，在
a lot of human in the loop of a lot of
很多驾驶过程中仍然有很多远程操控和人为干预，
this driving so we still haven't even
所以我们甚至还没有
like declared success but I think it's
宣布成功，但我认为它
definitely like going to succeed at this
肯定会成功，
point but it just took a long time and
只是需要很长时间。
so I think like like this is software is
所以我认为，这方面的软件真的非常
really tricky I think in the same way
棘手，就像
that driving is tricky and so when I see
驾驶一样棘手。因此，当我看到诸如“
things like oh 2025 is the year of
2025年是
agents I get very concerned and I kind
智能体元年”之类的说法时，我非常担心，我觉得
of feel like you know this is the decade
这才是
of agents and this is going to be quite
智能体的十年，而且这还需要相当长的
some time. We need humans in the loop.
时间。 我们需要人参与其中。
We need to do this carefully. This is
我们需要谨慎行事。 这是
software. Let's be serious here. One
软件。 咱们认真点儿。
more kind of analogy that I always think
我经常思考的另一个类比
through is the Iron Man suit. Uh I think
是钢铁侠战衣。 嗯，我想
this is I always love Iron Man. I think
这就是我一直都很喜欢钢铁侠的原因。 我觉得
it's like so um correct in a bunch of
它在很多
ways with respect to technology and how
方面，尤其是在技术及其发展前景方面，都非常正确
it will play out. And what I love about
。 我喜欢
the Iron Man suit is that it's both an
钢铁侠战衣的一点是，它既是
augmentation and Tony Stark can drive it
托尼·斯塔克可以操控的增强装备，
and it's also an agent. And in some of
也是一个特工。 在一些
the movies, the Iron Man suit is quite
电影中，钢铁侠战衣具有相当高的
autonomous and can fly around and find
自主性，可以飞行寻找
Tony and all this kind of stuff. And so
托尼等等。 所以，
this is the autonomy slider is we can be
这个自主性滑块可以让
we can build augmentations or we can
我们可以构建增强功能，也可以
build agents and we kind of want to do a
构建智能体，而我们希望
bit of both. But at this stage I would
两者都做一些。 但就目前而言，我认为应该
say working with fallible LLMs and so
与有缺陷的法学硕士等合作
on. I would say you know it's less Iron
。 我想说的是，你知道，你想要打造的与其说是钢铁
Man robots and more Iron Man suits that
侠机器人，不如说是钢铁侠战甲
you want to build. It's less like
。 与其说是
building flashy demos of autonomous
构建炫酷的自主
agents and more building partial
代理演示，不如说是构建部分
autonomy products. And these products
自主产品。 这些产品都
have custom gueies and UIUX. And we're
拥有定制化的用户界面和用户体验设计。 我们正在
trying to um and this is done so that
尝试这样做，目的是使
human is very very fast. But we are not
人类的生成验证循环非常非常快。 但我们并没有
losing the sight of the fact that it is
忘记，从
in principle possible to automate this
原则上讲，这项工作是可以自动化的
work. And there should be an autonomy
。 您的产品中应该有一个自主度调节
slider in your product. And you should
滑块。 你应该
be thinking about how you can slide that
思考如何调整
autonomy slider and make your product uh
自主性滑块，让你的产品
sort of um more autonomous over time.
随着时间的推移变得更加自主。
But this is kind of how I think there's
但我认为，
lots of opportunities in these kinds of
这类产品蕴藏着很多机会
products. I want to now switch gears a
。 现在我想稍微转换一下话题，
little bit and talk about one other
谈谈
dimension that I think is very unique.
我认为非常独特的另一个方面。
Not only is there a new type of
不仅出现了一种新型的
programming language that allows for
编程语言，它允许
autonomy in software but also as I
软件实现自主运行，而且正如我所
mentioned it's programmed in English
提到的，它是用英语编写的，英语
which is this natural interface and
是一种自然的界面语言，
suddenly everyone is a programmer
突然之间，每个人都成了程序员，
because everyone speaks natural language
因为每个人都说
like English. So this is extremely
像英语这样的自然语言。 所以这对我来说是一个非常
bullish and very interesting to me and
利好且非常有趣的迹象，
also completely unprecedented. I would
也是前所未有的。
say it it used to be the case that you
以前，你
need to spend five to 10 years studying
需要花五到十年时间学习
software. this is not the case anymore.
软件开发方面的知识才能胜任相关工作。 情况已经不同了。
So, I don't know if by any chance anyone
所以，我不知道有没有人
has heard of vibe coding.
听说过“氛围编码”（vibe coding）。
Uh, this this is the tweet that kind of
呃，这条推文算是把这件事
like introduced this, but I'm told that
引入了这个梗，但我听说
this is now like a major meme. Um, fun
它现在已经成了一个热门梗。 嗯，
story about this is that I've been on
关于这件事有个有趣的故事：我已经使用
Twitter for like 15 years or something
Twitter 大约 15 年了，
like that at this point and I still have
但我仍然
no clue which tweet will become viral
不知道哪条推文会爆红，
and which tweet like fizzles and no one
哪条推文会无人
cares. And I thought that this tweet was
问津。 我原以为这条推文会是
going to be the latter. I don't know. It
后者。 我不知道。
was just like a shower of thoughts. But
就像思绪如雨般涌来。 但这
this became like a total meme and I
完全变成了一个梗，我
really just can't tell. But I guess like
真的搞不清楚了。 但我想，
it struck a chord and it gave a name to
它触动了人们的内心，并为
something that everyone was feeling but
每个人都有的感受——但
couldn't quite say in words. So now
无法用语言表达——赋予了一个名称。 现在连
there's a Wikipedia page and everything.
维基百科页面都有了。
This is like
这就像
[Applause]
[掌声]是的，
yeah this is like a major contribution
这现在就像是一项重大贡献之类的
now or something like that. So,
。 嗯
um, so Tom Wolf from HuggingFace shared
，HuggingFace 的 Tom Wolf 分享了一个
this beautiful video that I really love.
我非常喜欢的精彩视频。
Um,
嗯，
these are kids vibe coding.
这些是儿童风格的编程。
And I find that this is such a wholesome
我觉得这段
video. Like, I love this video. Like,
视频非常励志。 我超喜欢这个视频。
how can you look at this video and feel
你怎么能看了这个视频还
bad about the future? The future is
对未来感到悲观呢？ 未来一片
great.
光明。
I think this will end up being like a
我认为这最终会成为进入
gateway drug to software development.
软件开发领域的敲门砖。
Um, I'm not a doomer about the future of
嗯，我对这一代人的未来并不悲观，
the generation and I think yeah, I love
而且我觉得，是的，我喜欢
this video. So, I tried by coding a
这个视频。 所以，我也试着写了一点代码，
little bit uh as well because it's so
因为这真的很
fun. Uh, so bike coding is so great when
有趣。 嗯，所以自行车编程非常棒，当
you want to build something super duper
你想要打造一些超级
custom that doesn't appear to exist and
定制的、似乎不存在的东西，而且
you just want to wing it because it's a
你只是想随性发挥一下，因为那天是
Saturday or something like that. So, I
星期六之类的。 所以，我
built this uh iOS app and I don't I
开发了这个 iOS 应用，虽然我
can't actually program in Swift, but I
实际上不会用 Swift 编程，但我竟然
was really shocked that I was able to
能开
build like a super basic app and I'm not
发出一个如此基础的应用，这让我非常惊讶，我就不
going to explain it. It's really uh
解释了。 这真的
dumb, but uh I kind of like this was
很蠢，但是，
running on my phone like later that day
那天我工作的时候，手机上正好运行着这个程序，然后
and I was like, "Wow, this is amazing."
我就想，“哇，这太棒了。”
I didn't have to like read through Swift
我不需要像那样花五天时间通读一遍 Swift 才能
that to like get started. I also
上手。 我还对一款
vipcoded this app called Menu Genen. And
名为 Menu Genen 的应用程序进行了 vipcode 编码。
this is live. You can try it in
这是现场直播。 您可以在 menu.app 中尝试一下
menu.app. And I basically had this
。 我遇到的
problem where I show up at a restaurant,
问题是，我去餐厅吃饭，
I read through the menu, and I have no
看了菜单，却完全不
idea what any of the things are. And I
知道上面的菜是什么。 我
need pictures. So this doesn't exist. So
需要图片。 所以这东西并不存在。 于是
I was like, "Hey, I'm going to bite code
我就想，“嘿，我要自己写代码
it." So, um, this is what it looks like.
。” 嗯，它看起来是这样的。
You go to menu.app,
你访问 menu.app，
um, and, uh, you take a picture of a of
然后，你拍一张
a menu and then menu generates the
菜单的照片，然后 menu 会生成
images and everyone gets $5 in credits
图片，每个人注册后都会免费获得 5 美元的积分
for free when you sign up. And
。
therefore, this is a major cost center
因此，这是
in my life. So, this is a negative
我生活中的一项主要开支。 所以，对我来说，这目前是一个负面的
negative uh, revenue app for me right
、收入负面的应用
now.
。
I've lost a huge amount of money on
我在菜单上赔了很多钱
Okay. But the fascinating thing about
好的。 但对
menu genen for me is that the code of
我来说，菜单生成器最吸引人的地方在于，
the v the vite coding part the code was
v 的代码，也就是 vite 编码部分的代码，
actually the easy part of v of v coding
实际上是 v 编码菜单中最简单的部分，
menu and most of it actually was when I
而且大部分实际上都是在我
tried to make it real so that you can
尝试将其变为现实的时候，这样你就可以
actually have authentication and
真正拥有身份验证、
payments and the domain name and averal
支付、域名和平均
deployment. This was really hard and all
部署。 这真的很难，而且
of this was not code. All of this devops
这一切都不是代码。 所有这些运维方面的
stuff was in me in the browser clicking
东西都让我需要在浏览器中点击各种
stuff and this was extreme slo and took
东西，这非常慢，又花了
another week. So it was really
一周时间。 所以，最令人
fascinating that I had the menu genen um
着迷的是，我只用了
basically demo working on my laptop in a
几个小时就在我的笔记本电脑上做出了菜单生成器的演示版本，
few hours and then it took me a week
然后却花了一周时间
because I was trying to make it real and
才把它变成现实，
the reason for this is this was just
原因很简单，这真的
really annoying. Um, so for example, if
很烦人。 嗯，举个例子，如果
you try to add Google login to your web
你尝试在你的网页上添加 Google 登录
page, I know this is very small, but
，我知道这只是很小的一部分，但是
this clerk library telling me how to
这个 Clerk 库里有大量的说明告诉我如何
integrate this. And this is crazy. Like
集成它。 这太疯狂了。
it's telling me go to this URL, click on
它就像在告诉我，去这个网址，点击
this dropdown, choose this, go to this,
这个下拉菜单，选择这个，去这里，
and click on that. And it's like telling
然后点击那个。 这就像是在告诉
me what to do. Like a computer is
我该怎么做。 就像电脑
telling me the actions I should be
告诉我应该
taking. Like you do it. Why am I doing
采取什么行动一样。 就像你做的那样。 我为什么要这样做
this?
？   我勒个去
What the hell?
？
I had to follow all these instructions.
我必须遵守所有这些指示。
This was crazy. So I think the last part
这太疯狂了。 因此，我认为
of my talk therefore focuses on can we
我演讲的最后一部分将重点讨论我们是否可以
just build for agents? I don't want to
只为代理构建？ 我不想
do this work. Can agents do this? Thank
做这份工作。 经纪人可以这样做吗？
you.
谢谢。
Okay. So roughly speaking, I think
好的。 所以粗略地说，我认为出现了
there's a new category of consumer and
一种新的
manipulator of digital information. It
数字信息消费者和操控者类别。 过去只有
used to be just humans through GUIs or
人类通过图形用户界面（GUI）或
computers through APIs. And now we have
计算机通过应用程序接口（API）进行交互。 现在我们有了
a completely new thing and agents are
全新的事物，代理是
they're computers but they are humanlike
计算机，但它们有点像人类，对吧？
kind of right they're people spirits
它们是人灵，
there's people spirits on the internet
互联网上有人类灵，
and they need to interact with our
它们需要与我们的
software infrastructure like can we
软件基础设施进行交互，比如我们能否
build for them it's a new thing so as an
为它们构建什么。这是一个新事物。举个
example you can have robots.txt on your
例子，你可以在你的域名上放置 robots.txt 文件，
domain and you can instruct uh or like
你可以指示或
advise I suppose um uh web crawlers on
建议网络爬虫
how to behave on your website in the
如何在你的网站上运行。
same way you can have maybe lm.txt txt
同样，你也可以放置 lm.txt
file which is just a simple markdown
文件，这是一个简单的 Markdown 文件，
that's telling LLMs what this domain is
它告诉 LLM（网络爬虫）这个域名是
about and this is very readable to a to
关于什么的，这对 LLM 来说非常易读
an LLM. If it had to instead get the
。 如果必须获取
HTML of your web page and try to parse
网页的 HTML 并尝试解析
it, this is very errorprone and
它，这将非常容易出错且
difficult and will screw it up and it's
困难，并且会搞砸一切，最终
not going to work. So we can just
无法成功。 所以我们可以
directly speak to the LLM. It's worth
直接和法学硕士（LLM）对话。 值得
it. Um a huge amount of documentation is
。 嗯，
currently written for people. So you
目前已经为人们编写了大量的文档。 所以你
will see things like lists and bold and
会看到列表、粗体字和图片之类的东西，
pictures and this is not directly
而这些内容是
accessible by an LLM. So I see some of
法学硕士（LLM）无法直接访问的。 所以我看到
the services now are transitioning a lot
现在有些服务机构正在将很多
of the their docs to be specifically for
文档转移到专门针对
LLMs. So Versell and Stripe as an
法学硕士（LLM）的文档上。 例如，Versell 和 Stripe
example are early movers here but there
是这方面的先行者，但
are a few more that I've seen already
我已经看到还有一些其他公司也
and they offer their documentation in
提供
markdown. Markdown is super easy for LMS
Markdown 文档。  Markdown格式对于学习管理系统（LMS）来说非常容易
to understand. This is great. Um maybe
理解。 太好了。 嗯，或许我可以
one simple example from from uh my
根据我的经验举一个简单的例子
experience as well. Maybe some of you
。 也许你们有些人
know three blue one brown. He makes
知道三种蓝色和一种棕色。 他
beautiful animation videos on YouTube.
在YouTube上制作精美的动画视频。
[Applause]
[掌声]
Yeah, I love this library. So that he
是的，我喜欢这个图书馆。 所以他
wrote uh Manon and I wanted to make my
写了 Manon，而我想自己做一个，
own and uh there's extensive
但是
documentations on how to use manon and
Manon 的使用方法有很多文档，
so I didn't want to actually read
所以我不想真的去读一遍
through it. So I copy pasted the whole
。 于是我把整个动画复制粘贴
thing to an LLM and I described what I
到 LLM 中，描述了我
wanted and it just worked out of the box
想要的效果，结果
like LLM just bcoded me an animation
LLM 直接就帮我生成了
exactly what I wanted and I was like wow
我想要的动画，我当时就想，哇，
this is amazing. So if we can make docs
这太神奇了。 所以，如果我们能让
legible to LLMs, it's going to unlock a
LLM（法学硕士）看懂文档，就能释放
huge amount of um kind of use and um I
大量的……用途，我
think this is wonderful and should
认为这很棒，应该
should happen more. The other thing I
更多地发生。 我
wanted to point out is that you do
想指出的另一点是，很
unfortunately have to it's not just
遗憾，你不得不这样做，这不仅仅是
about taking your docs and making them
将你的文档转换成
appear in markdown. That's the easy
Markdown 格式那么简单。 那只是最简单的
part. We actually have to change the
部分。 我们实际上需要修改
docs because anytime your docs say click
文档，因为文档中任何时候出现“点击
this is bad. An LLM will not be able to
这里”这样的语句都是不好的。 目前，LLM学位还无法
natively take this action right now. So,
直接执行此操作。 例如，
Verscell, for example, is replacing
Verscell 会将
every occurrence of click with an
每次点击替换为
equivalent curl command that your LM
等效的 curl 命令，您的 LM
agent could take on your behalf. Um, and
代理可以代表您执行该命令。 嗯，
so I think this is very interesting. And
我觉得这很有意思。 当然
then, of course, there's a model context
，还有 Enthropic 提供的模型上下文
protocol from Enthropic. And this is
协议。 这也是
also another way, it's a protocol of
另一种方式，一种
speaking directly to agents as this new
直接与代理人对话的协议，代理人是
consumer and manipulator of digital
数字信息的新消费者和操纵者
information. So, I'm very bullish on
。 所以，我非常看好
these ideas. The other thing I really
这些想法。 我非常喜欢的另一点
like is a number of little tools here
是，这里那里有很多小工具，
and there that are helping ingest data
它们可以帮助我们
that in like very LLM friendly formats.
以非常适合LLM的格式摄取数据。
So for example, when I go to a GitHub
例如，当我访问
repo like my nanoGPT repo, I can't feed
像我的 nanoGPT 仓库这样的 GitHub 仓库时，我无法将
this to an LLM and ask questions about
其提供给 LLM 并询问有关
it uh because it's you know this is a
它的问题，因为你知道，这是
human interface on GitHub. So when you
GitHub 上的人类界面。 所以，当你把
just change the URL from GitHub to get
GitHub 的 URL 改成导入
ingest then uh this will actually
格式时，它实际上会将
concatenate all the files into a single
所有文件连接成一个
giant text and it will create a
巨大的文本文件，并创建一个
directory structure etc. And this is
目录结构等等。然后就可以把它复制
ready to be copy pasted into your
粘贴到你
favorite LLM and you can do stuff. Maybe
喜欢的 LLM 编辑器里，开始进行各种操作了。 或许
even more dramatic example of this is
更引人注目的例子是
deep wiki where it's not just the raw
深度维基，它不仅仅是
content of these files. uh this is from
这些文件的原始内容。 呃，这是来自
Devon but also like they have Devon
Devon 的，他们
basically do analysis of the GitHub repo
基本上让 Devon 对 GitHub 仓库进行分析，
and Devon basically builds up a whole
Devon 基本上会
docs uh pages just for your repo and you
为你仓库构建一整套文档页面，你
can imagine that this is even more
可以想象，这
helpful to copy paste into your LLM. So
对于复制粘贴到你的 LLM 中会更有帮助。 所以
I love all the little tools that
我喜欢所有的小工具，
basically where you just change the URL
基本上你只需要更改 URL，
and it makes something accessible to an
就能让 LLM 访问某些内容
LLM. So this is all well and great and u
。 这一切都很好，
I think there should be a lot more of
我认为应该多一些这样的事情
it. One more note I wanted to make is
。 我还有一点想补充，
the future LLMs will be able to this is
未来LLM（学习型硕士）完全有可能做到——这
not even future this is today they'll be
甚至不是未来，而是现在——他们
able to go around and they'll be able to
可以四处走动，
click stuff and so on but I still think
点击各种东西等等。但我仍然认为，
it's very worth u basically meeting LLM
基本上应该让LLM更
easier for them to access all this
容易地获取所有这些
information uh because this is still
信息，这非常值得。因为
fairly expensive I would say to use and
使用这些信息仍然相当昂贵，而且
uh a lot more difficult and so I do
难度也大得多。所以我
think that lots of software there will
认为，很多软件都会
be a long tail where it won't like adapt
存在长尾效应，无法像应用
apps because these are not like live
程序那样灵活运用，因为这些软件不是实时
player sort of repositories or digital
播放器之类的存储库或数字
infrastructure and we will need these
基础设施，我们需要这些
tools. Uh but I think for everyone else
工具。 嗯，但我认为对其他人来说，找到一个
meeting in some middle point. So I'm
折衷方案是非常值得的。 所以，
bullish on both if that makes sense.
如果这么说你能理解的话，我对两者都持乐观态度。
So in summary, what an amazing time to
总而言之，现在正是
get into the industry. We need to
进入这个行业的绝佳时机。 我们需要
rewrite a ton of code. A ton of code
重写大量的代码。 大量代码
will be written by professionals and by
将由专业人士和
coders. These LLMs are kind of like
程序员编写。 这些LLM有点像
utilities, kind of like fabs, but
公用设施，有点像晶圆厂，但
they're kind of especially like
它们尤其像
operating systems. But it's so early.
操作系统。 但现在还太早了。
It's like 1960s of operating systems and
这就像 20 世纪 60 年代的操作系统，
uh and I think a lot of the analogies
而且我认为很多相似之处都是相通的
cross over. Um and these LMS are kind of
。 嗯，这些学习管理系统就像是会
like these fallible uh you know people
犯错的人类
spirits that we have to learn to work
灵魂，我们需要学会与他们合作
with. And in order to do that properly,
。 为了更好地实现这一目标，
we need to adjust our infrastructure
我们需要调整我们的基础设施以适应这一需求
towards it. So when you're building
。 所以，在构建
these LLM apps, I describe some of the
这些 LLM 应用程序时，我会介绍一些
ways of working effectively with these
有效使用这些
LLMs and some of the tools that make
LLM 的方法，以及一些使之成为
that uh kind of possible and how you can
可能的工具，以及如何
spin this loop very very quickly and
快速地启动这个循环，并
basically create partial tunneling
基本上创建部分隧道
products and then um yeah, a lot of code
产品，然后，是的，
has to also be written for the agents
还需要为代理编写大量代码
more directly. But in any case, going
。 但无论如何，回到
back to the Iron Man suit analogy, I
钢铁侠战衣的比喻，我
think what we'll see over the next
认为在接下来的十年里，我们大致会看到的情况
decade roughly is we're going to take
是，我们将把
the slider from left to right. And I'm
滑块从左向右移动。 我
very interesting. It's going to be very
很有趣。
interesting to see what that looks like.
看看最终效果会是什么样子，应该会很有意思。
And I can't wait to build it with all of
我迫不及待地想和大家一起把它建成
you. Thank you.
。 谢谢。